Guide to the Columbian and Hesperian Literary Society Records, 1848-1942
Duke University. University Archives
Columbian and Hesperian Literary Society records 1848-1942
Duke University. University Archives
Trinity College (Durham, N.C.)
8.5 linear feet Extent: 350 Items
The Columbian Literary Society was founded in 1846. The Hesperian Literary Society was founded in 1851. Records of both the Columbian Literary Society and Hesperian Literary Society documenting their activities. Included are numerous minute books, roll books, treasurer's books, book lists, constitutions and bylaws as well as some correspondence and programs for events co-hosted by the societies.
UA.31.09.0003
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Columbian and Hesperian Literary Society Records were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1971.
Historical Note
The Columbia Literary Society was first organized in 1846 at Union Institute. The Society grew with the school, witnessing the founding of Trinity College and its development into Duke University. In 1881, the CLS started the College Herald, forerunner of the Chronicle.
The Hesperian Literary Society was founded in 1851 at the suggestion of President Craven, because in his opinion, all first class colleges had two societies. According to tradition, it was called "Hesperian" because it was originally intended to be joined by boys from Western North Carolina.
The two societies are the only student organizations known to have existed when Normal College became Trinity College in 1859. They each had libraries and competed in acquiring books. The joint efforts of both societies led to the creation of The Archive and The Chronicle publications. Additionally, they both accumulated larger number of books than the college library.
According to the Trinity College Catalogue, by 1860 each society held 2,200 volumes, while the school itself held only 650. In 1887, new president John Franklin Crowell persuaded the literary societies to merge their collections with that of the college, creating a combined library of 10,000 volumes. The new library was housed on the second floor of the old Trinity College chapel, and Crowell claimed to have catalogued each of the books himself.
After Trinity moved to Durham in 1892, the library occupied a large single room in the Washington Duke Building, the main building of the campus. One student from each of the two literary societies served as librarians.
Both societies continued to co-exist until the Hesperian Literary Society dissolved in 1931-1932, although a similar organization, the Hesperian Union, organized in 1937. The Columbian Literary Society ended in 1938.
Collection Overview
Contains correspondence, reports, financial information, roll books, record books, and minute books of the Columbian and Hesperian Literary Societies. The two societies conducted many joint debates so their papers are in one collection. Most of the collection is in oversize boxes. The collection ranges in date from 1848-1942.
Subject Headings
Union Institute (Randolph County, N.C.); Normal College (Randolph County, N.C.); Trinity College (Randolph County, N.C.) -- Students; Trinity College (Durham, N.C.). Columbian Literary Society; Trinity College (Durham, N.C.). Hesperian Literary Society; Trinity College (Durham, N.C.). Library; Trinity College (Durham, N.C.) -- Students; Duke University -- History -- 20th century; Duke University -- Students -- Societies, etc.
Related Material
Trinity College Library records, 1892-1924
Duke University Archives
Contents of Collection
- Columbian Literary Society, 1848-1942, (8) Boxes
  - HOLY BIBLEundated (Box 1)
  - Minutes1848-1850 (Box 2)
  - Minutes1850-1852 (Box 2)
  - Minutes1860-1870 (Box 2)
  - Minutes1870-1875 (Box 2)
  - W.H. Wannamaker Papers Correspondence File, 1942 (Box 3)
  - Columbian Literary Society Constitution Revision,1860-1873 (Box 3)
  - Account of Books Borrowed,1886-1887 (Box 3)
  - Account of Loans from the Society Library, 1883-1884 (Box 3)
  - Record of Society’s Library, 1866 (Box 3)
  - Honorary Members List,1851-1881 (Box 3)
  - Minutes1876-1882 (Box 4)
  - Minutes1882-1891 (Box 4)
  - Minutes1891-1898 (Box 5)
  - Minutes1927-1930 (Box 5)
  - Minutes of the Executive Committee1913-1933 (Box 5)
  - Constitution and Bylawscirca 1912 (Box 6)
  - Constitution and Bylaws1901 (Box 6)
  - Constitution and Bylawscirca 1860s (Box 6)
  - Book List1871, undated (Box 6)
  - Treasurer's Book1855-1859 (Box 6)
  - Treasurer's Book1861-1869 (Box 6)
  - Treasurer's Book1872-1875 (Box 6)
  - Treasurer's Book1875-1877 (Box 6)
  - Treasurer's Book1892-1896 (Box 6)
  - Minute Book1911-1920 (Box 7)
  - Executive Committee's Book1896-1902 (Box 8)
  - Censor's Book1890-1892 (Box 8)
  - Constitution1887 May (Box 8)
  - Roll Book1910-1921 (Box 8)
  - Book Record1877-1879 (Box 8)
  - Treasurer's Book1860-1864 (Box 8)
  - Constitution and Bylaws1873-1888, 1901-1916 (Box 8)
  - Fact Sheet, History1937 (Box 8)
- Hesperian Literary Society, 1851-1930, (10) Boxes (Box 8)
  - Constitution and Bylaws1895 (Box 8)
  - Executive Committee's Book1898-1901 (Box 8)
  - Minutes1867-1868 (Box 8)
  - Minutes1851-1853 (Box 9)
  - Minutes1854-1866 (Box 9)
  - Minutes1866-1879 (Box 9)
  - Minutes1874-1879 (Box 9)
  - Constitution and Bylaws, 19281899 (Box 9)
  - Constitution and Bylaws, 19281928 (Box 9)
  - Minutes1879-1883 (Box 10)
  - Minutes1883-1888 (Box 10)
  - Minutes1888-1890 (Box 10)
  - Minutes1891-1892 (Box 10)
  - Minutes1892-1893 (Box 10)
  - Minutes1893-1898 (Box 11)
  - Minutes1899-1917 (Box 11)
  - Treasurer's Book1875-1878 (Box 12)
  - Treasurer's Book1891-1895 (Box 12)
  - Treasurer's Book1896-1903 (Box 12)
  - Treasurer’s Book1903-1913 (Box 13)
  - Roll Book1919-1926 (Box 13)
  - Treasurer's Book1870-1874 (Box 14)
  - Treasurer's Book1881-1885 (Box 14)
  - Librarian's Account Book1854-1858 (Box 14)
  - Librarian's Account Book1882 (Box 14)
  - Librarian's Account Book1884 (Box 14)
  - Book Record1853-1873 (Box 14)
  - Roll Book1914-1920 (Box 15)
  - Treasurer's Account Book1912-1921 (Box 15)
  - Minutes1917-1930 (Box 16)
  - Book Record1876 (Box 17)
  - List of Bookscirca 1900 (Box 17)
  - Debate Council Minutes1911-1923 (Box 17)
  - Debate Council Minutes1928-1929 (Box 17)
- Columbian and Hesperian Literary Societies, 1860-1930, (2) Boxes (Box 17)
  - Invitation1890 (Box 17)
  - Events Annoucements, Programs1870-1930 (Box 17)
  - College Herald1882 June (Box 17)
  - Society Correspondence1886-1911 (Box 17)
  - Society Correspondence, offical business1887-1890 (Box 17)
  - Trinity Chronicle Correspondence1909-1914 (Box 17)
  - Rules, Regulations and Minutes1891-1905 (Box 17)
  - Executive Committee Materials1916-1920 (Box 17)
  - Constitutions and Bylaws1928, undated (Box 17)
  - Cover of Trinity Magazine1883 (Box 17)
  - Address Delivered for both Societies1860 (Box 17)
  - Trinity Chronicle Bylaws1908 (Box 15)
  - Ervin A. Thompson Address1860 (Box 15)